应当处死!
He deserves to die!
这个人和"神的儿子"是一伙的!
This man walks with this "Son of God"!
我不是! 我不认识他!
I do not! I don't know him!
啊!
Aah!
我愿贡献出我自己的墓地 作为您儿子的安息之地
I would like to offer my own tomb as your son's final place of rest.
他被处决是因为反复亵渎神明
He was killed for the repeated blasphemy
声称自己是弥赛亚
of claiming to be the Messiah.
如果他是呢?
And if he was?
一旦他们认识到你们的启示仍是威胁
Once the Romans realize your message remains a threat,
他们会将你们连根拔除
they will root you out.
那个拿撒勒人也不过是血肉之躯
The Nazarene was only ever flesh and blood.
我要你在亚利马太的坟墓布下寺庙的守卫
I want you to post temple guards at Arimathea's tomb.
必须封死墓穴
It must remain sealed.
在第三日 他保证会起死回生
On the third day, he promises to rise from death.
我会在墓穴外安排一个小的守卫队
I will post a small guard outside the tomb.
封条已经被破坏了
The Roman seal has been broken.
坟墓已经打开了 那个拿撒勒人... 不见了
The tomb is now open, and the Nazarene... is gone.
"不见了"是什么意思?
What do you mean, "gone"?
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第2集
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
耶路撒冷
第三日
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调: 影子
翻译: Astral 飘飘行天下 猫呗
翻译: 舒大卷子 鸟生鱼汤 波特妹子
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
怎么了?
What is this?
有人在昨晚侵入了那个拿撒勒人的坟墓
The Nazarene's tomb was raided overnight.
那些罗马的卫兵呢?
What of the Roman guard?
逃走了
Fled.
你在耍我吗?
Do you take me for a fool?
墓地被一块巨大的石头封住了
A massive stone sealed that tomb.
仅仅一个人
One man alone
是绝对推不动它的
could never have moved it.
肯定有很多人
There must have been many.
那你看见了几个人?
So, how many did you see?
只有一个 但他不是凡人
One, but it wasn't human.
不可能!
Impossible!
他们肯定在撒谎
They're clearly lying.
不管怎样 我们不能让他们的话
Nevertheless, we cannot allow their account
演变成危险的谣言
to be the basis of a dangerous rumor.
那就快点想办法别泄露了风声
Then think quickly to ensure that it can't.
如果被问起来 你们就说
If asked, you're only to repeat
你们在执勤的时候睡着了
that you fell asleep on duty.
你们在睡觉时候
And while you slept,
那个拿撒勒人的门徒打开了墓穴
the Nazarene's men tore open the tomb
并偷走了他的尸体
and stole his corpse.
你们该庆幸没有因为玩忽职守
Count yourselves lucky your dereliction of duty
被我的丈夫剥夺你们的神职
doesn't compel my husband to strip you of the priesthood.
我再也不要见到你们
I never want to see you again.
那个拿撒勒人的追随者
The Nazarene's followers
妄图伪造他的复活
are attempting to fake his resurrection.
这件事怎么就没完了?
Why won't this business end?
这个耶稣怎么就不能
Why couldn't this Jesus
继续当个死人呢?
just stay dead?
你要保持头脑冷静 特别是现在
You need to keep a cool head, now more than ever.
你一向以精明智慧著称 该亚法
You are celebrated for your shrewd intelligence, Caiaphas.
在彼拉多发现事实真相
Draw on every last drop
并且藉此来对付我们之前
before Pilate discovers what has happened
得想尽一切办法
and uses it against us all.
赶在那群加利利人宣扬他们的骗局之前
Find the Nazarene's body
找到那个拿撒勒人的尸体
before the Galileans begin to publicize their hoax.
我们应该把他的尸体吊在城墙外示众
We shall hang his corpse outside the city wall.
真是松了口气
What a relief,
终于能离开这鬼地方了
to be finally leaving this damned hole.
我还从没像现在这样
I've earned my time
挤出时间逃离这地方
away from this place like never before.
我中午就能收拾好行李
I'll be packed by midday.
拜托 别弄这么久
Please, no longer.
我可等不及让地中海的风
I can't wait for the Mediterranean winds
把你那些噩梦和无稽的幽灵之说
to blow away the last traces of your nightmares
给吹个一干二净
and apparitions.
我的梦很清晰
My dream was clear.
你钉死的是受众神青睐的人
The man you crucified was favored by the gods.
我们都会因为他的死而受苦的
We shall all suffer for his execution.
我们真得让你回归文明社会了
We really need to get you back to civilization.
它空了
It's empty.
什么?
What?
那个墓穴
The tomb.
早上好 巡抚
Good morning, Governor.
确实挺好的
It was.
我想昨晚的地震没有打扰您睡觉吧?
I trust the tremor in the night didn't disturb your sleep?
一点都没有
Not for a moment.
那么...
Now...
你们怎么来了 先生们?
What brings you here, gentlemen?
我想亲自过来
I wanted to come in person
感谢您这几个礼拜来 在那个拿撒勒人的事情上
to thank you for your guidance with the Nazarene
对我的指导
these past weeks.
不必言谢
Your gratitude is unnecessary.
管理是我的职责所在
Governance is my job.
今天是第三日了 对吧?
It is the third day, is it not?
对的
It is.
他还是个死人吗?
And he remains dead?
是的
He does.
就像我还有自然规律所预测的那样
As I and every law of nature predicted.
确实如此
Indeed.
不管我被安放在帝国的任何职位
Wherever I am posted in the empire,
无论我的职位带来什么益处
whatever benefits occupation brings,
总是有些人
there are always those
妄图挑战罗马帝国的权威
who seek to challenge the authority of Rome,
而结局通常只有一个
and the outcome is usually the same.
您的支持是莫大的帮助
Your support is a great help.
当我面临严格与公正二选一的时候
When faced with the choice of being either firm or fair,
我就明白了严格些通常更有益处
I've learned that firm generally pays the greater dividend.
再见 先生们
Good day, gentlemen.
您走好
Safe passage.
他还什么都不知道
He knows nothing.
要不了多久他就知道了
We don't have long before he does.
我们必须找到尸体
We need to find that body.
- 我正在找  - 哼 那就找得更努力点
- I'm working on it.  - Well, work harder.
哦!
Oh!
长官
Sir.
这是什么情况?
What is this?
有个拿撒勒人坟墓的守卫有事想跟您报告
A member of the guard from the Nazarene's tomb to speak to you.
他为何颤抖?
Why does he tremble?
- 因为害怕 - 害怕什么?
- With fear. - Of what?
害怕您得知他跟我说的事后 可能会带来的后果
Of what may follow when he tells you what he told me.
我就出价那么多
That is my price.
好久不见了啊
Long time, no see.
祭司
Priest.
你想要什么?
What do you want?
这一刻 只要你听我说
For the moment, just your attention.
接下来 要你帮忙找一具尸体
And then your help to find a corpse.
主 我的神 你是以色列的希望
Lord our God, you are the hope of Israel,
谁若离弃你 必蒙羞耻
and all who forsake you shall be ashamed,
因为他们离弃了唯一的真神
for they have forsaken the one true God,
离弃了生命水的源泉
the fountain of living water.
你是有福的 主 我的神
Blessed are you, Lord our God.
使我免于敌人的伤害
Protect me from my enemies
使我前行的路上保持刚强
and keep me strong in the way ahead.
你要求的每件事
What have I done
我除了支持 可曾有过异议?
but support you in every way you asked?
我要抗议 您这是严重侵犯了我神圣的...
I must protest at this gross violation of my sacred...
我究竟做了什么 竟招致这样的不敬?
What have I done to deserve such disrespect?
如果您坚持要继续谈话
If you insist on holding a conversation,
至少让我穿上衣服
at least allow me to dress.
待在水里
Stay in the water
你这鳝鱼般油滑的人
like the eel you are.
巡抚 我知道您在生气
Governor, I can see you're angry.
你误导我相信
You led me to believe
那个拿撒勒人的坟墓昨夜一切安好
the night passed peaceably at the Nazarene's tomb,
而我现在已经知道事实远非如此
which I know now is far from the truth.
巡抚...
Governor...
今早你究竟有没有对我撒谎?!
Did you or did you not lie to me this morning?!
我知道您有多期盼
I know how much you've been looking forward
与您妻子一同到凯撒利亚去旅行
to traveling to Caesarea with your wife,
而我本来相信我可以解决这个情况
and I believed I could resolve the situation
而不会扰乱您的计划
without disrupting your plans.
那结果如何?
And have you?
我们正在采取行动
Action is under way.
同时 对耶稣的个人崇拜
Meanwhile, this Jesus cult
每分每秒都在增长
grows stronger by the hour.
要不了多久 它就会
Soon, it will draw
把那些狂徒和叛乱分子全引到耶路撒冷来
every crackpot and revolutionary into Jerusalem
他们一心一意就只想挑战我们所有人
with the sole aim of challenging us all.
我敢肯定 是那些加利利人偷走了尸体
The Galileans stole the body. I'm sure of it.
我们要能找到他们 就能找到尸体
And if we find them, we'll find the corpse.
向我报告他们的行踪
Send me the information on their whereabouts
立刻去办...
immediately...
我会亲自处理这件事情 一次性给解决干净
And I will deal with this matter once and for all.
我这就去办
I shall.
我不明白
I don't understand.
这怎么可能呢?
How is this possible?
我们就把他安放在这里
We laid him here.
谁会这么想方设法地弄走他的尸体?
Who would go to such lengths to take his body?
杀了他还不够... 他们还得彻底擦去所有痕迹
Killing him wasn't enough... They had to wipe out all trace.
但这裹尸布... 是叠好的
But the shroud... It's folded.
我想不出究竟有谁会...
I don't know who could have...
- 为什么破坏掉罗马政府的封条?  - 我不知道
- Why break the Roman seal?  - I don't know.
今天正是第三日
It is the third day.
你敢相信吗?
Do you dare to believe?
你发现什么了?
What did you find?
没有... 我们什么都没发现...
Nothing... We found nothing...
但什么都清楚了
And everything.
你为何要哭?
Why are you crying?
- 是你把他带走了吗?  - 谁?
- Have you taken him?  - Who?
如果是你把他带走了 求你
If you've taken him, please,
告诉我在哪儿...
tell me where...
我会去找他
and I will get him.
玛利亚...
Mary...
拉比
Rabbi.
我们发现石头滚在一边
We found the rock rolled back,
罗马人的封印也被破坏了!
the Roman seal broken!
- 要是彼拉多认为是我们干的...  - 他为什么这么想?
- If Pilate thinks we're responsible...  - why would he?
除了我们谁还会冒这么大险把他的尸体运回来?
Who else would take that kind of risk to get his body back?
约翰相信先知以赛亚的预言解释了所发生的一切
John believes Isaiah's prophecy explains what's happened.
先知预言了弥赛亚
The prophet foretold that the Messiah
会像羊被牵到宰杀之地
would be led like a lamb to slaughter,
为我们的过犯受害 死在恶人身旁
pierced for our transgressions, die beside the wicked,
与财主同被安葬!
and be laid to rest with the rich!
- 约翰!  - 在过去的三天里
- John!  - In the last three days,
我亲眼看见这些事应验!
I've seen all these things!
但是你相信他已经死而复生了吗?
But do you believe he has risen from the dead?
他曾保证这些都会发生
It's what he promised would happen.
罗马皇帝的封印已经被破坏了
The emperor's seal is broken.
我们究竟是走还是留?
Do we stay or go?
是罗马人!
Romans!
- 我们得走了  - 等等
- We need to leave.  - Wait.
我们必须要冷静
We need to calm down.
我们不能排除一个可能 坟墓是被当权者打开掏空
We cannot rule out that the tomb was opened and emptied
好把我们逼出来然后一网打尽
by the authorities to flush us out and round us up.
我看到他了
I saw him.
谁?
Who?
耶稣
Jesus.
他和我说话了
He spoke to me,
就像我在你面前说话一样
as clearly as I'm speaking to you now.
玛利亚...
Mary...
他还活着
He's alive.
他刚才站在我面前
He stood before me
叫出了我的名字
and spoke my name.
这会是真的吗?
Can it be true?
你怎么看 彼得?
What do you think, Peter?
我想...
I think I feel...
他离去后我倍感痛苦
pain at his absence.
感到无比罪恶...
Great guilt...
因为没能陪伴他到最后
because I wasn't with him at the end.
还有羞耻!
And shame!
我很想告诉他我对不起他
I so want to tell him I'm sorry.
愿你们平安
Peace be with you.
拉比!
Rabbi!
不敢相信你亲眼所见吧
Can't you believe your own eyes,
是否以为你们所见的是魂?
do you think you're looking at a ghost?
魂又如何能有骨有肉呢?
What ghost carries flesh and bones?
- 有什么吃的没有?  - 有 有
- Is there any food?  - Yes. Yes.
这就是我从前与你们同在之时 所告诉你们的话
This is what I told you while I was with you.
摩西的律法 先知的书
Everything written about me in the laws of Moses,
和诗篇上所记的
the prophets,
凡指着我的话 都必须应验
and the psalms must be fulfilled.
是多马!
It's Thomas!
拉比...
Rabbi...
你们简直想不到我一路是怎么回来的
You won't believe the journey I've made to get back.
我本来确信我被跟踪了
I was convinced I was being followed,
然后我就迷糊了 也记不起来
and then I became confused and couldn't remember
哪条街哪座房子才是对的
which was the right street or the right house.
直到我看到...
It was only when I saw...
怎么了?
What?
是耶稣
Jesus.
- 我知道  - 不是
- I know.  - No.
多马 他刚才在这
Thomas, he was here.
什么?
What?
耶稣刚才就在这房间里
Jesus was just here in this room.
和我们一起分吃面包
He broke bread with us.
你是在和我开无聊的玩笑吗
Are you playing a sick joke on me
就因为我最后一个回来?
because I'm the last to get back?
不是
No.
那么 耶稣...
So, Jesus...
刚才和你们在一起?
was here with you all?
是的
Yes.
你们把我当成什么人
What kind of fool do you take me for
竟会蠢到无凭无据就相信这么一个故事?
that I would believe a story like that without proof?
你们究竟怎么看我
What kind of opinion must you have of me
才会相信我会这么轻易就被愚弄?
to believe I'd be so easily duped?
- 多马 这是事实  - 够了!
- Thomas, it's the truth.  - Enough!
我两夜没合眼了
I haven't slept for two nights.
几乎什么都没吃
I've barely eaten.
我拼尽全力赶回来
It was all I could do to come back at all.
多马 我们...
Thomas, we...
给我停下!
Stop this now!
去墓地自己看吧
Go to the tomb and see for yourself.
用你的亲眼见证
See with your own eyes.
我非看见他手上的钉痕
Unless I see the nail marks in his hands,
用指头探入那钉痕
put my finger in them,
又用手探入他的肋旁
unless I put my hand in the spear wound itself,
我总不信
I will not believe.
你觉得他死了 一切都结束了?
You think he's dead and this is finished?
还能怎样?
What else?
还有真相
The truth.
玛利亚...
Mary...
去坟墓那
Go to the tomb.
你来找我是对的
You do well to come to me.
不 不! 别这样! 不!
No, no, no, no! No! No, no!
叫你们要看守好坟墓!
You were told to guard the tomb!
够了
Enough.
我最不能容忍的一件事就是...
One thing I cannot abide above all else...
不忠
Disloyalty.
啊! 我们速战速决
Ugh! Let's do this quickly,
要不然这臭味引来的问题可不远止老鼠那么点
before the stench attracts more questions than rats.
他身上有十字架刑罚留下的伤痕...
He has the wounds from the crucifixion...
手上 脚上 还有肋旁
Hands, the feet, and the side,
头上有荆棘刺的伤痕 背上有
Thorn marks on the forehead and the welts from the lash
鞭打的伤口 都是新鲜的
across his back, all fresh.
但这不是那个拿撒勒人
But this is not the Nazarene.
我说让你找那个拿撒勒人的尸体
I told you to bring me the Nazarene's body,
你却做了这么一个... 血肉模糊的遇害者尸体!
and you produce this... mutilated, murdered carcass!
只要你告诉民众他就是拿撒勒人
People will take him for the Nazarene
他们会相信的...
if you tell them it's him...
而且只要你把尸体吊的够高
and if you hang it a good distance from the ground,
看起来就几乎一模一样了
the resemblance will be striking.
在拿撒勒人的尸体没有找到的情况下
And in the event that the Nazarene's body is not found,
这难道不是一个替代方案吗?
isn't this an alternative?
我不能冒着被指控
I cannot risk being accused of
蓄意编造骗局欺骗大众的风险
orchestrating a fraud to deceive our nation.
可惜 民众没你想的那么蠢
Unfortunately, the people are not as stupid as you think.
拿走
Take it away.
简直玷污了我的圣洁
I'm made filthy by this.
神殿守卫在重新封印坟墓
Temple guards are resealing the tomb.
他们为什么这么做?
Why would they do that?
好假装他的尸体还在里面
To pretend his body remains inside,
扑灭他复活的谣言
kill any rumors that he's risen.
现在你信了吗 多马?
Now do you believe, Thomas?
我们已经看见主了
We saw him.
我们每个人都摸了他
Each one of us touched him,
与他同坐 同吃 同笑
sat with him, ate with him, laughed with him.
但我并没有
But I did not.
怎么可能我们所有人
How can each of us be mistaken
在完全一样的时间
in exactly the same way
犯完全一样的错误?
at exactly the same time?
多马...
Thomas...
我的主...
My Lord...
你因看见了我
Now that you have seen for yourself,
才信
you believe
那没有看见就信的人
Blessed are they who have not seen me
有福了
and still believe.
站到一边!
Stand aside!
找到他们
Find them.
彻查这里!
Tear the place apart!
逃犯!
Runners!
去屋顶! 快!
Roof! Go!
去楼梯! 快!
Stairs! Go!
让开!
Get out of the way!
罗马人来了!
Romans!
城门口见 快走!
I'll see you at the gate. Go!
- 他们去哪里了?!  - 你为什么想知道?!
- Where will they go?!  - Why do you need to know?!
他们没做错任何事!
They've done nothing wrong!
你要知道 有些人
You know, some men hesitate
在审问中打女人会下不去手
before striking a female under interrogation.
我可不是这样的人 不要跟我耍花招
I'm not one of them. Do not play games with me.
他们会去哪里?
Where will they go?
你儿子的尸体在哪儿?
Where is your son's body?
不在这里
Not here.
在哪儿?
Where is it?
他母亲都不知道
If his own mother doesn't know,
我怎么会知道?
why would I?
他们跑太快了
They had too much of a start.
封锁城市
Lock down the city.
这边
This way.
我在哪儿?
Where am I?
暂时是安全的地方
Safe, for now.
你为什么要帮助我们?
Why are you helping us?
历史会判定究竟是你的方法还是我的
History will determine whether your path or mine
方法会将罗马人驱逐出犹太省
will drive the Romans from Judea.
另外 罗马人的敌人就是我们的朋友
In the meantime, an enemy of theirs is a friend of ours.
我让我的朋友们去城门口集合
I told my friends to make their way to the city gate
然后想办法找到一条去加利利的路
so we can find a way out to Galilee.
那里的士兵会少些
There are fewer soldiers there.
我们可以帮忙
We can help.
靠杀人来帮忙就不用了
Not by killing.
不像这些侵占我们土地的人 我们只把死亡视作最终手段
Unlike our occupiers, we only take life as our last resort.
我们很多祭司都因为你在拿撒勒人这件事上
There are many who are unsettled
与彼拉多交往过密感到不安
by how close you've been with Pilate over the Nazarene.
他们害怕你无法掌控这个联盟!
They fear it's an alliance you can't control!
大祭司必须保持
The high priest must maintain
一个微妙的平衡 既能够影响巡抚的决断
a delicate balance between influencing the Governor
又能够与他合力对抗我们的民众!
and joining forces with him against our people!
民众要是像我们所希望的那么温顺倒好了
If only our people were as benign as we might wish.
他们是不是认为我和彼拉多商量
Do they think I consulted with Pilate
处决一个疑似犹太人的同胞?
over the execution of a fellow Jew likely?
即使是现在 我还在怀疑我们做的究竟正不正确
Even now, I question whether it was the right course of action.
但我做了决定
But I made a decision.
他们就会看到你像个领导人一样
And they will see you standing by it
坚定守护了自己的决定
like a leader of conviction.
坚定的决心
Strong resolve
是领导的基石 神父
is the bedrock of leadership, father,
而不是简单的去满足民意
not the easy appeasement of the public will.
请不要进去! 先生
don't go in there! Sir, please!
起先 你煽动处决无辜的传道者
First, you instigate the execution of a harmless preacher,
接着你亵渎了我的坟墓
then you desecrate my own tomb
又打扰了亡者!
to interfere with a corpse!
有再大的权力也不该这样行事!
By what authority do you behave like this!
没有人打扰了亡者 约瑟
No one's interfered with the corpse, Joseph.
如果有人亵渎了你的坟墓
And if your tomb's been desecrated,
那也一定与我毫无关系
it wasn't by anyone associated with me.
你是在用罗马的油
You've extinguished a small Jewish flame
来熄灭零星的犹太之火
by smothering it with a Roman oil.
你终究会被这火给反噬 该亚法
You may yet get burned by this, Caiaphas.
天真的蠢人
Naive fool.
但却是很有影响力的蠢人
But an influential one.
任何妄图给以赛亚的预言添油加醋的
Any attempt to breathe life into Isaiah's prophecy
都得镇压
must be quashed
免得煽动起民众幻想来反抗我们!
before it ignites public imagination against us!
我正是在朝着这个方向努力
I am working on precisely that.
那么 我能建议让你更努力一些吗?
Well, may I suggest you work on it harder?
站好! 顶住防线!
Stand firm! Hold the line!
准备好
Be ready.
这就送你们出去
We'll get you out.
拿一个
Take one.
时机终于到了
The time has come.
打开城门!
Open the gates!
打开城门! 打开城门! 打开城门!
Open the gates! Open the gates! Open the gates!
打开城门! 打开城门!
Open the gates! Open the gates!
顶住防线!
Hold the line!
顶住!
现在就走
Go now.
跟上!
Come on!
你们已经搜城搜了好几天
You've been scouring the city for days.
这伙人怎么可能就这么凭空消失?
How can a group of men simply disappear?
他们比我们更熟悉耶路撒冷
They know Jerusalem better than we do.
我也许不知道他们在哪 巡抚
I may not be able to tell you where they are, Governor,
但我知道他们没有带着尸体逃出去
but I do know they didn't escape with the corpse.
他们把尸体藏起来了?
They left it at their hideout?
我亲手把那个地方查了个底朝天
I tore the place apart with my own hands.
他们逃走的时候没带着尸体 也没尸体留在那
None had it when they ran, and it wasn't left behind.
我恨死这个鬼地方了
How I loathe this place,
这么热...
its heat...
还有热昏了头的民众
and its overheated people.
每块石头都见证了一个奇迹
Every stone a witness to a miracle,
每条死狗
every dead dog
都是恶灵的凶兆
a portent of supernatural malice,
再微小的天气突变
the slightest inconsistency in the weather
都是世界末日的前奏
a prelude to the end of the world.
我看到我现在本该在去往地中海的路上
I can see the road I should now be on to the coast,
克劳迪娅陪在身边
Claudia by my side,
离开这座城市越远 她就变得越正常
becoming more her usual self with every mile from the city.
但是我们仍然在这
But we're still here,
该死的拿撒勒人堵住了我们的出路
that damned Nazarene blocking our exit.
好吧 我们可是罗马人
Well, we are Rome.
是时候由我们来结束这个故事了
It's time we shut this story down.
加利利
要多久才能收网?
How long till we bring in the nets?
还早
Not yet.
难道没有可能到现在已经有鱼
Wouldn't any fish likely to have swum into the nets
在晚上游进网里了吗?
during the night have done so by now?
黎明的时候鱼会更活跃
They're more active at dawn.
黎明都过了
Dawn's over.
我教过你如何收税吗?
Do I tell you how to collect taxes?
没有
No.
那就不要教我怎样捕鱼
Then don't tell me about collecting fish.
- 你真的不觉得...  - 再说一个字 就把你踢下水
- Do you not think...  - Another word, you're going over the side.
- 我来帮你  - 还有我
- I'll help.  - And me.
我不明白
I don't understand it.
往常每年这个时候 海里到处都是鱼
The seas used to be boiling with fish this time of year.
我们应该把捕到的那些扔回海里
We need to throw back the few that we have caught.
也许该在我说收网的时候收起来
Perhaps if you brought the nets in when I said.
请闭上嘴!
Please shut up!
收获怎么样?
How's your catch?
烂透了!
Poor!
你们把网洒在船的右边
Cast your nets on the right-hand side.
左边或右边 没什么分别
Left or right, it won't make any difference.
你们把网洒在船的右边
Cast them on the right-hand side.
嚯!
Ho!
彼得!
Peter!
是主
It's him.
彼得!
Peter!
彼得...
Peter...
当你说我会三次不认你的时候
When you told me I would deny you three times,
我以为那绝不可能
I thought it impossible.
我以为你根本不了解我
I thought you don't know me at all.
但你比我还要了解我自己
But you knew me better than I know myself.
彼得...
Peter...
你爱我吗?
Do you love me?
你知道我爱你
You know I love you.
你喂养我的小羊
Feed my lambs.
你真的爱我吗?
Do you truly love me?
你知道我爱你
You know I do.
你喂养我的羊
Feed my sheep.
彼得
Peter,
你爱我吗?
do you love me?
我爱你
I love you.
你跟从我吧
Then follow me.
彼拉多的愤怒让你苦恼 你还对我视而不见
Pilate's tantrum has vexed you, and I am invisible.
怎么回事?
What is it?
彼拉多我能应付
Pilate I can handle.
- 但是你的父亲  - 原来如此!
- Your father, however.  - Ah!
他忘了我是大祭司
He forgets that I'm high priest.
我想可能他的女儿
I think perhaps his daughter
有时也忘记了
forgets sometimes, too.
哦 你务必要原谅他
Oh, you must forgive him.
他像父亲般爱着你
He loves you like a son.
而我是像妻子般爱着你
And I love you like a wife.
你有我和他共同的支持
You have his support and mine.
你还想奢求什么呢?
What more could you possibly want?
大祭司
High priest.
怎么了?
What is it?
是看守拿撒勒人坟墓的祭司们
The priests guarding the Nazarene's tomb.
他们怎么了?
What of them?
其中两位发现被人谋杀
Two of them found murdered,
而其余的都失踪了
and the others are missing.
谋杀?
Murdered?
彼拉多要立刻见您
Pilate wishes to see you straight away.
预言说我必受害
It was prophesized that I would suffer
第三日从死里复活
and rise from the dead after three days.
坚信吧 彼得
Believe, Peter,
圣灵降临在你们身上
and the power of the holy spirit
你们就必得着能力
will come to you.
何时?
When?
回到耶路撒冷等待即可
Go back to Jerusalem and wait.
只有那时你才准备好
Only then will you be ready
去传道
to spread the word.
为我如此 彼得
Do this for me, Peter,
而有一天你会为我而死
and one day you will die for me.
你做好准备了吗?
Are you ready to do that?
是的
I am.
你们作我的见证 从耶路撒冷起
You will be my witnesses in Jerusalem
到犹太全地和撒玛利亚
and in all Judea and Samaria
直到地极
and to the ends of the earth.
你们往普天下去 传福音
Go into the world and preach the gospel
给万民听
to all creation.
这一切即将结束
This will all soon be over.
巡抚
Governor.
罗马帝国的兴盛 该亚法
The Roman Empire prospers, Caiaphas,
不是因为其压榨民众之少
not because it consumes lesser civilizations,
而是因为它包容民众
but because it embraces
并于他们构成一种合作关系
and forms partnerships with them.
从最高层次上说 这只有互相信任
At the highest level, this can only happen in a spirit
- 才能实现  - 我理解
- of mutual trust.  - I understand that.
是吗?
Do you?
把守卫们带过来
Bring in the guards.
守卫?
Guards?
那些你坚持要我安排在拿撒勒人墓地的守卫
Roman guards you insisted I place upon the Nazarene's tomb
那些我发现
and guards who I have discovered
在半夜离职弃岗的守卫
abandoned their post in the middle of the night.
一次又一次地
Time and again,
我相信你能
I entrusted you to bring
处理好这桩烂摊子
this sorry business to a close,
该亚法
Caiaphas.
而一次又一次地 你让我失望
Time and again, you've failed to do so,
所以现在必须由我出面
so now I must.
你害我的祭司被杀...
You had my priests killed...
不许插嘴!
I'm speaking!
你应该把这当成
You should consider this
市政管理的一课
a lesson in civic administration.
如果你控制不了谣言...
If you cannot control a story...
就杀死它
kill it.
巡抚 求你
Governor, please.
我怀着诚实和忠诚来找您
I come to you in good faith and loyalty,
因为我的荣誉感不允许我
'cause my honor wouldn't allow me
和其他人一样逃走躲起来
to run and hide with the others.
我明白...
I understand...
也很高兴
and I am glad of it.
谢谢您 巡抚
Thank you, Governor.
但是你 也是那晚的目击者
But you, too, were a witness that night.
而你来找我
And you came to me
不是出于诚实和忠心
not out of good faith and loyalty,
而是为了救你自己的狗命
but to save your own skin
而出卖你的同伴们...
at the expense of your comrades...
他们是好人...
Good men...
本不该死
who really didn't deserve to die,
不像你这该死的胆小狗
unlike a cowardly dog who does.
终于...
Finally...
重生的预言
the prophecy of the resurrection
和这些人一样消逝了
lies as dead as these men.
让那个拿撒勒人的信徒
Let the Nazarene's followers
尽管带着他腐烂的尸体逃亡吧
run where they like with his rotting corpse.
他们一旦露面 就会被抓住处死的
They won't surface without being caught and executed.
我的妻子还在等我
My wife is waiting for me,
我们俩还等着去海边
and the coast is waiting for us both.
把这收拾干净
Clean this up.
下集预告...
Next Sunday...
施舍几块钱吧 大人
A few coins, master.
站起来
Rise up.
因为耶稣 这个人又能走路了
It's for Jesus, this man walks again.
随着这位父亲越发相信上帝
As the father's belief grew stronger,
他对抗帝国的决心也日益坚定
so does his will to defy the Empire.
我从彼此身上汲取力量
We draw strength from each other.
为他传道
Spread his word.
终结这个流言 永绝后患
Shot this story down, once and for all.
他们会杀掉你吗?
Will they kill you?
我不知道
I don't know.